<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dorcas: or, A perfect patterne of a true disciple A sermon preached by Bartholomew Parsons B. of Divinity and rector of Ludgershall in the country of Wilts.</title>
            <author>Parsons, Bartholomew, 1574-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105866</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841592</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841592</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6186</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09054)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6186)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1325:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dorcas: or, A perfect patterne of a true disciple A sermon preached by Bartholomew Parsons B. of Divinity and rector of Ludgershall in the country of Wilts.</title>
                  <author>Parsons, Bartholomew, 1574-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Turner printer to the famous Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A perfect patterne of a true disciple.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6186:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DORCAS: OR, A PERFECT PATTERNE OF A TRUE DISCIPLE.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached by <hi>Bartholomew Parſons</hi> B. of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity and Rector of <hi>Ludger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ioh. 15.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Herein is my Father glorified, that yee beare much fruit, ſo ſhall yee be my Diſciples.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 31.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Shee ſtretcheth out her hand to the poore, yea ſhee reacheth forth her hands to the needy.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Turner</hi> Printer to the famous Vniverſity. 1631.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6186:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6186:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRED, MY LOVING FRIEND <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> FRANCIS PILE</hi> BARONET.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORTHY SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Oly <hi>Iob</hi> being about to vttter a divine medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture reſurrection, cryeth out, <hi>Oh that my words were written now, Oh that they were printed in a Booke. Iob. 19.23.</hi> And you of late being the Principall Auditor, where according to the gift giuen to me, J vttered this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Meditation, conceived vpon an excellent patterne in my Text, both of good workes in generall, and of
<pb facs="tcp:6186:3"/>Almeſ-deeds in ſpeciall, the best of workes, which ſhall be remembred and rewarded at the laſt reſurrection afore and aboue all other workes, walked in the ſame Spirit with that righteous man, in deſiring that theſe ſame words might be written vnto you, and not vaniſh away in the houre and aire wherein they were vttered: J haue therefore tranſcribed this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and doe willingly and deſeruedly Dedicate to your ſelfe this piece of my labours. And ſo much the rather J preſent it to you, becauſe as face an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to face in water, Prov. 27.19. ſo both your ſelfe &amp; your worthy Lady anſwere fully to this face of charity and almeſ-doing repreſented here to you in this Diſciple <hi>Dorcas,</hi> in the ſowing plentifully and ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:6186:3"/>at the ſet times weekely, the ſeede of your almes at your gates to the poore round about yuo: which J write not out of any flattery: (from which both by nature and conſcience J am averſe,) but as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians</hi> in alike caſe <hi>2. Cor. 8.1.3.</hi> to beare witneſſe of the grace of God beſtowed on you both, who are mette together in another <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Dorcas</hi> abounding in this worke of the Lord. As you haue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore worthily begunne; ſo happily goe on in ſowing the ſeed of your almes plentiouſly, that you may reape plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly in the day of the Lord. For though you ſeeme to the world to caſt your bread vpon the waters, where it is loſt, yet after many dayes you ſhall finde it againe, even in the great day
<pb facs="tcp:6186:4"/>of the Lord. <hi>The poore may ſay vnto thee, that I in receiving of Almes giue no leſſe vnto thee, then thou in beſtowing them giueſt vnto mee. For if there were not ſome to receiue thine Almes, thou couldeſt not giue earth and receiue heaven,</hi> as <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Auſtin</hi> ſayth. And in the meane ſeaſon, God that is rich to all, will ſo bleſſe your basket and your ſtore, that alwayes hauing ſufficiencie in all things, you may ſtill abound in this worke. For as <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth, <hi>Almeſ-doing maketh not any man poore, but enricheth him, for it is promiſed, giue, and it ſhall be giuen you:</hi> and againe, <hi>that thou mai'ſt be rich, giue thy goods liberally: that thou mai'ſt
<pb facs="tcp:6186:4"/>gather, ſcatter: follow the ſower, ſow in bleſſings, that thou mai'ſt reape in bleſſings:</hi> in his <hi>53.</hi> and <hi>68. Homilie</hi> to the people of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the God of Heaven bleſſe You, and your worthy Lady, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the bleſſings of Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and Earth beneath, but alſo with all Spirituall bleſſings in Chriſt Jeſus; that when you haue finiſhed your courſe happily in this world you may raigne eternally in the World to come; So wiſheth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant in our Maſter Chriſt Ieſus <hi>BARTHOL. PARSONS.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From my houſe at <hi>Collingborne</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 1. 1631.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6186:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6186:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Actes 9.36.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now there was at <hi>Ioppa</hi> a certaine Diſciple, named <hi>Tabitha,</hi> which by interpretation is called <hi>Dorcas:</hi> This woman was full of good workes, and almeſ-deedes which ſhee did.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O that queſtion of King <hi>Lemuel, [Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon]</hi> in that Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy taught him by a woman <hi>[his mother] who can finde a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous woman,</hi> Prov. 31.10. arguing and intimating die rarity of good women; wee may returne here an <hi>inventa eſt,</hi> and cry out with that paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate exclamation of <hi>Archimedes,</hi> a famous
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6186:6"/>Mathematician, when he had found out a Mathematicall experiment, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>I have found; I have found; ecce hîc, behold here is one;</hi> and ſo much the ſooner haue wee found, with <hi>Iaacob,</hi> becauſe the Lord our God hath brought one to our hands, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.10. beautified and beatified with all graces accompanying ſalvation in woman, <hi>Faith, and Charity, and Holineſſe with ſobriety.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. For that wee might not count her an alien, but one of the houſhold of faith, <hi>ſhe is a Diſciple;</hi> (&amp; Diſciples and Chriſtians are <hi>termini con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertibiles,</hi> of equivalent ſignification <hi>Act.</hi> 11.26) one that was not aſhamed of Chriſt and his words, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.26. that we may be aſſured that ſhee profeſſed not to know Chriſt, &amp; deny him in her works, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Shee is a good tree; bringing forth good fruites,</hi> Mat. 7. <hi>joyning vertue with her faith,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. and ſhewing her faith by her good workes, or that onely ſome good was found in her, as in <hi>Ieroboams</hi> ſon, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 14.13. ſome gleaning grapes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6186:6"/>as the ſhaking of an Oliue tree, <hi>Iſa</hi> 17.6. <hi>Shee is full of good workes,</hi> defectiue and behind in no gift, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7. or that ſhee ſerued God only in holines in the works of piety, and not in righteouſneſſe in the works of charity, (as too many put aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe things which God hath joyned together) ſhe diſtributeth to the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Saints, <hi>doth almeſ-deeds;</hi> and as ſhe aboundeth in every thing, ſo in this gift alſo, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7. ſoweth the ſeed of her almes plentiouſly, <hi>is full of almeſ-deedes which ſhe did.</hi> But that by my ordering of things here, I may further your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of them, (as <hi>ordo eſt mater memoriae,</hi> order is the mother of memory) obſerue I pray you in this narration a twofold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of this vertuous woman; 1. by her civill condition, <hi>There was at</hi> Ioppa <hi>a certaine Diſciple named</hi> Tabitha, <hi>which by interpretation is called</hi> Dorcas, 2. by her religious diſpoſition, <hi>this woman was full of good workes and almeſ-deedes which ſhee did.</hi> In her civill ſtate and condition wee
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6186:7"/>haue 1. her place of habitation, <hi>Ioppa,</hi> 2 her name, either propounded, named <hi>Tabitha,</hi> or expounded, <hi>which by interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is called Dorcas.</hi> In her religious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition, wee haue 1. her profeſſion <hi>a Diſciple,</hi> 2. her expreſſion of it, either ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally in good workes, amplified by the meaſure and extent, <hi>full of good workes;</hi> or ſpecially in almeſ-deeds, being of the ſame ſize <hi>full of almeſ-deeds which ſhe did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning her civill ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, her habitation and denomination, being but the outward skin and rine of the Text, in reſpect of the pith within: I will not according to the proverbe <hi>haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in cortice,</hi> ſticke in the barke. Onely <hi>in tranſitu,</hi> in our paſſage heare and beare a word or two of the propounding and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding of her name, for if wee ſtrike this rocke the waters will guſh out, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.6 <hi>ſhee was named Tabitha, which by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation is called Dorcas.</hi> Names in Scriptures are impoſed either vpon ſome ſpeciall accident, or intent and purpoſe.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6186:7"/>Vpon ſome ſpeciall accident, as <hi>Iſaacks</hi> name of laughter, becauſe <hi>Sarah</hi> laughed at the promiſed of him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.13. <hi>Iacobs</hi> of ſupplanting; becauſe he tooke his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the heele in the birth of them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25 26. and <hi>Pharez</hi> his name ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing breach, or diviſion; becauſe he made a breach in the birth, comming forth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his brother that offered firſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.29. Vpon ſome ſpeciall intent, either for memoriall of benefits receiued, as <hi>Iſhma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> the hearing of God, becauſe God heard <hi>Abrahams</hi> prayer for a ſonne, <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.15. as <hi>Solomon, Iedidiah</hi> loued of the Lord, becauſe God loued him, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.24. Or of ſome duties to be done, as <hi>Iudah</hi> hath his name of prayſes, becauſe the Lord was to be prayſed for him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.35. as <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> called by Chriſt <hi>Boanerges</hi> ſonnes of thunder, becauſe they ſhould thunder in their doctrine, and lighten in their liues, <hi>Marke</hi> 3.17. and that name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all names <hi>Ieſus</hi> a Saviour, becauſe he ſhould ſaue his people from their ſins,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6186:8"/>
               <hi>Matt.</hi> 1.25. And here happily the name <hi>Tabitha</hi> in Syriacke, and in the Hebrew <hi>Tſibjah,</hi> or as ſome will haue it <hi>Thabia, (Bullinger in locum)</hi> ariſing of roote <hi>nabat</hi> ſignifying to ſee, (as in the interpretation of it in the Greeke <hi>Dorcas</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of ſeing) was giuen her accidentally of the ſharpeneſſe of her ſight, wherein the Roe-bucke excelleth, (as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith) and of which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi> hath a ſaying, <hi>oculos caprearum talpa contemnit,</hi> the blind moule deſpiſeth the eyes of the Roe-bucke. Sure I am that ſhe was ſharpe ſighted in look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on things eternall, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18, that the eyes of the mind were enlightned <hi>to know what was the hope of her calling, and what the riches of the glory of Gods inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the Saints, Epheſ.</hi> 1.18. that with <hi>Simeon</hi> the eyes of her inward man ſaw the Lords Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.16 &amp; that they were happy in ſeing his day, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Now in that Spirit ſpeaking here to the Churches, would interpret this Hebrew or Syriacke name in the Greeke
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6186:8"/>tongue, wherein it writeth; <hi>Tabitha</hi> by <hi>Dorcas</hi> or Roe-bucke: our learning here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is, that all things in the Church muſt <hi>be done to edification,</hi> 1 .<hi>Cor</hi> 14.26. and that whatſoever is ſpoken in a <hi>ſtrange tongue</hi> muſt be <hi>interpreted that the Church may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue edifying</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.5. and this is the way of God in the ſanctuary. <hi>Emanuell</hi> a ſtrange word in the greeke tongue, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted <hi>God with vs, Matt.</hi> 1. So <hi>Rabbi</hi> is interpreted <hi>Maſter; Meſſias,</hi> the <hi>Chriſt; Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,</hi> a <hi>ſtone;</hi> all one chapter <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. ſo <hi>Boanerges,</hi> the <hi>ſonnes of thunder, Mar.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Barnabas,</hi> tke <hi>ſonne of conſolation, Actes</hi> 4. <hi>Abba, Father, Rom.</hi> 8.15. Now if the wiſedome of the ſpirit would interpret names to vs whereof wee may be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, without forfetting the freehold of eternall life, much more would it haue the whole Scriptures (<hi>which were written for our learning, Rom.</hi> 15.4. and are able to make vs <hi>wiſe vnto ſalvation.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.) interpreted and expounded vnto vs in a knowne tongue, for edification,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6186:9"/>exhortation, and comfort. <hi>Qui in modico fidelis, &amp; in majori fidelis. He that is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in a little matter, will be faithfull in a greater, Luke</hi> 16.10. If a name muſt be ſpoken to vs in our owne tongue, much more muſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.11. <hi>the great myſteries of godlineſſe,</hi> in a language that we vnderſtand. And of that I dare be bold to ſay, that from the beginning it was ſo. The doctrine of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> did not ſo vaniſh away, as the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> did: (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in 1. <hi>Homily</hi> on <hi>Iohn</hi>) but the <hi>Syrians, Aegyptians, Indians, Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Aethiopians,</hi> and innumerable other nations tranſlating them into their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, of barbarous men, learned the heavenly Philoſophy. So <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his 2. <hi>booke of Chriſtian doctrine, chap.</hi> 5. ſaith, <hi>that the divine Scripture proceeding from one language, being ſpread abroad farre and wide by the diverſe tongues of Interpreters, was made knowne to the Gentiles for their ſalvation.</hi> And <hi>Theodoret</hi> moſt plainly in his <hi>firſt booke of curing the maladies of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6186:9"/>Grecians, The Hebrew bookes were not only turned into the Greeke language, but alſo into the Roman, Egyptian, Perſian, Indian, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menian, Scythian, and even the Gothicke language;</hi> and that I may ſpeake once for all, into all the languages which the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles vſe vnto this day. Can wee praiſe the Papiſts then in condemning and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as impoſſible and vnprofitable the turning of the divine oracles into our mother tongue, (which was their old Tenent) or if they be interpreted and tranſlated, either in their forbidding that in the publique and common vſe of the Church they ſhould be read or ſung in the vulgar tongues: (<hi>ſo doth the Counſell of Trent in the</hi> 22. <hi>Seſſion chapt.</hi> 8. <hi>and the</hi> 9. <hi>Canon:</hi>) or elſe in affecting ſuch obſcurity, and filling their tranſlation with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words borrowed from the <hi>Hebrew, Syriacke, Greeke,</hi> &amp; <hi>Latine,</hi> that it may be ſayd of their tranſlation as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher ſayd of his bookes, that they were <hi>edita &amp; non edita,</hi> publiſhed and not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6186:10"/>Of this kinde are their <hi>Archiſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, azimes, depoſitum, dydrachme, domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, evangelize, holocausts, hoſtes, Neophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, paraclete, paraſceve, prepuce, repropitiate, reſuſcitate, ſabbatiſme,</hi> and ſuch like, whereof an Engliſh man may cry out, how can I vnderſtand vnleſſe I had the gift of tongues? If I know not the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the voyce, <hi>I ſhall be vnto him that ſpeaketh Barbarian, and hee ſhall be a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barian to mee,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 11. But here is not my reſt, I paſſe therefore from her civill ſtate and condition to her religious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition firſt in her profeſſion being a Diſciple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A certaine Diſciple,</hi> The originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> feminine according to her ſexe, a <hi>Diſcipleſſe,</hi> a <hi>ſhee Diſciple,</hi> as <hi>Anna</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Propheteſſe, Luke</hi> 2.36. Excellent and honourable are the ſtiles and titles giuen in holy writ to the profeſſours of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, importing the dignity and duty of their calling. They are named the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>elect of God,</hi> of their calling &amp; choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6186:10"/>out of the world: <hi>Saints,</hi> of their <hi>ſanctification, ſonnes of God,</hi> of their <hi>adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; veſſels of mercy,</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent forgiueneſſe of their ſinnes and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture glory: <hi>believers, faithfull</hi> men of their <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>profeſsion: brethren, houſhold of faith,</hi> of their <hi>vnion</hi> and <hi>ſociety</hi> amongſt themſelues: <hi>devout men,</hi> of their <hi>religion, Diſciples of Chriſt Ieſus</hi> the author and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of our faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. But the name <hi>Diſciple,</hi> is the moſt auncient, the moſt frequent in the new Teſtament gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to all the faithfull, the Apoſtles not excepted, who are called the <hi>twelue Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, Matt.</hi> 10.2. Now the Scripture in the Evangeliſt doth not onely call thoſe twelue his Diſciples, but all thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving in him, were by his teaching in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed to the kingdome of heaven, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine in his</hi> 2. <hi>booke of the conſent of the Evangeliſts, Chap.</hi> 17. To be a Diſciple then, is to heare &amp; learne of God by the miniſtery of the Goſpell, the way of peace, the myſteries of Godlineſſe. And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6186:11"/>
               <hi>Tabitha</hi> hath this name here, becauſe with <hi>Mary</hi> ſhee ſate at Ieſus feete and heard his words, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.39. with <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> ſhee attended to thoſe things which were ſpoken of Gods Miniſters, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend then the imitation hereof, not only to her ſexe, but to all the Saints, all that will call on the name of the Lord, to learne of her to be ſchollers in Chriſts ſchoole, <hi>to ſit at the beautifull feete of them that preach the Goſpell of peace, and bring glad tidings of good things, Rom.</hi> 10.15. For all muſt learne of them that prophecy, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31. of ſuch <hi>Epaphraſſes</hi> as are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters of God for them, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.7. all muſt <hi>obey</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>be perſwaded &amp; taught of them that haue the overſight of them, and ſuffer the word of exhortation, Heb.</hi> 13.17.22. all muſt <hi>receiue the word ingraffed with meekeneſſe, Iam.</hi> 1.21. <hi>heare the Prophets that are raiſed vp vnto them. Deut.</hi> 18.15. heare and receiue them as an Angell of God, yea as Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Let vs ſo heare the Goſpell</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:6186:11"/>(<hi>Auſtin</hi> in his 30 tract vpon <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>as wee would heare the Lord himſelfe if he were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent now, for that precious thing which ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the Lords mouth was both written for vs, and is reſerved for vs, &amp; is rehearſed to vs:</hi> and againe, <hi>that which is to be learned by a man, let a Chriſtian learne without any pride, let vs not tempt him in whom we haue beleeued, leaſt being deceiued by ſuch ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and frowardneſſe of our common enemy, we ſhould refuſe to goe into the Church to heare and learne the Goſpell, or to read a booke, or to heare a man read and preach.</hi> And in his booke of Catechiſing the rude, chapt. 12. hee would haue men ſuch cheerefull hearers, <hi>that if our preaching at any time be colder then vſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is, it might be quickened and kindled by their vnvſuall hearing and attending.</hi> But in theſe late and worſer dayes, if wee ſurvay this weake ſexe, wee may every where finde <hi>ſilly women ever learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. never worthy of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6186:12"/>the name of Diſciples, or elſe ſo farre in the other extreme, that in ſtead of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, they will be Doctors, preſume to teach, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. according to that of <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> in an epiſtle to <hi>Paulinus, the babling old woman will teach the ſcripture before ſhe hath learned it,</hi> or elſe ſo farre from all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learning in Chriſts ſchoole, that with the Scribes and Phariſees they <hi>will neither enter into the kingdome of heaven, nor ſuffer others, Matt.</hi> 23.13. but with their grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother <hi>Eue</hi> are tempters of others to ill, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. with <hi>Ieſabell</hi> are ſtirrers of others to worke wickedneſſe, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 21.25. with <hi>Iobs</hi> wife are perſwaders to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe, <hi>Iob.</hi> 2. with <hi>Solomons</hi> wiues are inticers to idolatry, 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 11.4. with <hi>Herodias</hi> movers to murther, <hi>Matt.</hi> 14. with the <hi>harlot</hi> allures to luſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.18. with <hi>Michall</hi> deſpiſers of religious zeale in others, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. and with thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of by <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.13. ſuch as learne to be <hi>idle, wandring about from houſe to houſe, and not onely idle, but tatlers alſo,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6186:12"/>and buſiebodies ſpeaking things which they ought not.</hi> But ſcarcely any where can we finde thoſe women that learne in ſilence, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. that with the honourable Dames of <hi>Berea receiue the word with all readineſſe of minde, and ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures whether thoſe things are ſo, Act.</hi> 17.11.12. and with <hi>Damaris</hi> there, verſe 34 cleaue vnto <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching: that with the women, and <hi>Mary</hi> the mother of Ieſus continue with the Apoſtles in the exerciſe of religion, act. 1.14. and with <hi>Mary Magdalen, Ioanna,</hi> and <hi>Suſanna,</hi> are with Chriſt, whileſt hee is preaching and ſhewing the glad tidings of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven, <hi>Luke.</hi> 8.1.2. Nay if wee runne too and fro, through the ſtreetes of our Ieruſalem, and ſee, and know, and ſeeke in the broad places therof, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.1. where can we find any Diſciples vnleſſe ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> found at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that haue Learned nothing, ſoe ignorant that they cannot tell whether there be an holy Ghoſt or no, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.2.3 any ſuch tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6186:13"/>ſchollers as <hi>Cornelius,</hi> with his words in their mouthes, to Chriſts miniſters, <hi>we are here as in the preſence of God, to heare the things that are commanded you of God, Act.</hi> 10.33. any that preſſe vpon them to heare the word of God, as thoſe did, <hi>Luke</hi> 5.1. <hi>Diogenes</hi> comming into <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> ſchoole, &amp; being often rejected by him, yet ſtucke there ſtill, and when on a time <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> offered to ſtrike him with his ſtaffe, he bowed his head and ſaid, <hi>Beate me if thou wilt, but thou ſhalt finde no ſtaffe ſo hard wherewith thou ſhalt driue me away, ſo long as thou ſpeakeſt any thing.</hi> According to which effect, <hi>Augustine</hi> on <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth, <hi>If thou canst teach me that I know not, I ought not onely to indure thee patiently in words, but alſo beating me with ſtripes</hi> But now though wee ſpeake the hidden wiſedome of God, in a myſtery able to make man wiſe vnto ſalvation, and not the periſhing wiſedome of this world (as the old Philoſophers did) wee haue neede of roddes and ſtaues to driue men
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6186:13"/>to vs, to compell them to come in, that Gods houſe may be full of Diſciples. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where we may finde <hi>Despiſers</hi> ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then <hi>Diſciples, prophainers</hi> rather then <hi>profeſſours, good companions</hi> rather then <hi>good Chriſtians, brethren in evill</hi> rather then <hi>holy brethren, children of the Devill</hi> rather then <hi>ſonnes of God;</hi> and the <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues of Satan</hi> rather then the <hi>houſhold of Faith:</hi> yea the very names of Diſciple, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, beleever, profeſſour, Saint, faithfull, (which ſhould be our crowne and our joy) are laughed to ſcorne by miſcreants which yet would be good Chriſtians. But let them be aſſured that if they be aſhamed to be Chriſts Diſciples here, to learne and know him, that hee will be aſhamed of them hereafter <hi>Luke</hi> 9.26. that he will not then know them for any of his.</p>
            <p>Wee ſee that this woman hath begun to runne well, to witneſſe a good confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, let her ride on proſperouſly as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Pſaml.</hi> 45.4. for ſhee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6186:14"/>lacketh yet one thing comprehending in it many things to make her a compleate Chriſtian, ſhee muſt not onely profeſſe well, but alſo expreſſe it, not onely haue her eares opened to learne Chriſts will, <hi>mine eares haſt thou opened,</hi> but her heart and hand ready to doe it, <hi>I delight to doe thy will, thy law is within my heart Pſal.</hi> 40.6.8. for <hi>Chriſtianum facit vita &amp; profeſsio,</hi> as <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>life and profeſsion together make a Chriſtian.</hi> Let vs marke then how theſe meete and kiſſe each other in her, for her profeſſion ſhe is a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> for her <hi>profit,</hi> ſhee is generally <hi>fruitfull in good workes.</hi> Now concerning good workes here mentioned, <hi>Pilate</hi> in the ſpirit of ſcoffing or curioſity asked our Saviour, <hi>what is the truth? Iohn</hi> 18.38. but wee in the ſpirit of meekeneſſe may well aske here, what good workes are? Good workes then (as I haue learned at the feete of a <hi>Gamaliel</hi> of ours, <hi>Zanchy</hi> on the 1. chap. of the <hi>Philip.</hi> verſe 11.) <hi>are workes and actions aſwell inward as outward:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6186:14"/>they be thoughts in the minde, and elections in the will, or words vttered by the tongue, or deedes which may be done by a righteous man as he is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in any part of his ſoule or body. For as an actuall ſinne is any thing ſayd, or done, or thought againſt the law of God, ſo a good worke, (and as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> calleth it in his 1. epiſt. cap. 3.) righteouſneſſe is any thing ſpoken, or thought, or done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law of God. The holy Ghoſt for our better direction and for diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth ſometimes tripartite good workes into 1. <hi>ſobriety</hi> in the vſe of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, as meate, drinke, apparell and the like: 2. <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> in our dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with men: 3. <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> in our duties to God; that we ſhould <hi>liue ſoberly, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and godly in this preſent world, Tit.</hi> 2.12. ſometimes hee doth more briefely bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partite them into <hi>holineſſe,</hi> in the duties of the firſt table that concerne <hi>Gods worſhip;</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> in the duties of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table, that reſpect our <hi>neighbours
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6186:15"/>good, that wee might ſerue him in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of our life, Luke</hi> 2.75. And ſo doth our Saviour into the firſt and great commandement which is, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule, and with all thy minde; and the ſecond is like to it,</hi> which is, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe. Matt.</hi> 22.37.38.39.40. Now this being written for our learning, we muſt learne of this Diſciple, this learner in in Chriſts ſchoole, to joyne with our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion practice, with our hearing doing, with our faith vertue 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. with our ſhew of godlineſſe the power of it in our liues. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. with our knowledge of God the ſervice of him. 1. <hi>Chr.</hi> 28 9. with our profeſſing to know God a manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it in our workes 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. with our calling of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> father a doing of the workes of <hi>Abraham, Iohn</hi> 8.39. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours of the Goſpell muſt haue their converſation <hi>as becometh the Goſpell of Chriſt, Phil.</hi> 1.27. <hi>VValke worthy of the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6186:15"/>wherewith they are called; Epheſ.</hi> 4.1. &amp; <hi>worthy of the Lord vnto all pleaſing, Col.</hi> 1.10. &amp; <hi>adorne themſelues with good works,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.10. <hi>This is a faithfull ſaying, and theſe things I will that thou affirme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, that they which haue beleeued in God, might be carefull to maintaine good workes, Tit.</hi> 3.8. Men learne the trades of this world to practiſe them, and the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of godlineſſe are taught vs that wee may turne wordes into workes, as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſayth in his tract of ordering our liues. <hi>It profiteth not to haue learned what wee ſhould doe, and not to doe it,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> in an epiſtle) it is better not to know a thing, then to learne it with danger: and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and in his 2. homily on the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation: As it booteth not for a great tree to be greene, and yeeld no fruit, ſo it profiteth not to be called a Chriſtian, and not to haue Chriſtian workes:</hi> and the ſame father in his booke of 83 <hi>questions,</hi> and 76 <hi>questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> ſayth, that the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>I ſuppoſe that a man is justified by faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6186:16"/>the workes of the law, are not ſo to be vnderstood, that when a man hath receiued faith, we ſhould call him just, though hee liue ill.</hi> But in this point wee that glory in God <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.17. and are called Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, are ſo bad ſchollers that if my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares, I could not ſufficiently bewaile our wants of fruites anſwerable to our profeſſion; wee make our boaſt of Gods law amongſt vs, but through our brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it, we diſhonour God, and cauſe his name to be blaſpheemed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.23.24. with the <hi>Iewes Ier.</hi> 7. wee cry <hi>templum Domini, the Temple of the Lord,</hi> God is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, and wee are his temple, but we amend not our wayes: we come and ſtand before God in his houſe, as a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that would do righteouſly, but when we are gone, wee doe all abominations, ſteale, murther, committe adultery, ſweare raſhly and falſely, drinke till wee are drunke, giue others drinke till they are drunke alſo, and runne to all exceſſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6186:16"/>of riot. Wee are indeed baptized vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> Gods Miniſters whom he hath ſent to baptize, and eate the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall meate, and drinke the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall drinke, but pleaſe not God in our liues and converſations, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2.3.4.5. with <hi>Simon Magus</hi> wee haue a kinde of temporary beliefe, but our hearts are not right in the ſight of God, but wee are in the gall of bitterneſſe, and in the bond of iniquity, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.13.21.23. we haue <hi>Iacobs</hi> voyce, ſmooth and bleſſed words, but <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands, rough and curſed deedes; with the figge tree we haue the leaues of an outward profeſſion, but want the fruits of an holy converſation; with <hi>Iudas</hi> vve are numbred amongſt Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſit at table vvith him, but betray him aſſoone as vvee are gone out; vvee heare but vvee do not, vvith out mouthes and bodily preſence vvee ſhevve much loue, but our <hi>hearts runne after covetouſneſſe, Ezec.</hi> 33.31. and all kinde of vvickednes. In a vvord, vve haue much knovvledge,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6186:17"/>no charity, a dead faith, a faith of Devils, but no workes; Chriſts greateſt friends and they of his owne houſhold are his greateſt enemies, being as <hi>Bernard</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines in his time, <hi>all friends, and all ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; all neceſſaries, and all adverſaries; all neere, and yet all ſuch as ſeeke their owne. Videtur bone Ieſu</hi> (as <hi>Hugo</hi> complaineth in his time) <hi>O good Ieſu the whole company of Chriſtians ſeemeth to haue conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, and they which are firſt in thy Church, are first in perſecuting of thee.</hi> Woe, woe vnto vs for our ill liues, ſhall our outward profeſſion, our dead and devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh faith ſaue vs without good workes? Marke wee that faithfull ſaying of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> in his booke of faith to <hi>Peter</hi> the Deacon, cap. 40. <hi>Beleeue it for a truth and doubt not of it, that not all which are baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within the Catholicke Church ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue eternall life, but they who after baptiſme receiued liue well: for as infidels, heretickes, and ſchiſmatickes ſhall not haue the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven, ſo vitious Catholickes ſhall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6186:17"/>not poſſeſſe it.</hi> Next wee haue her good workes amplified by the extent,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Full of good worke]</hi> ſhe was filled with the fruits of righteouſneſſe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.11. like thoſe water pottes at the wedding, that were full to the brimme <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. and ſhee gaue to God and man good meaſure, <hi>preſſed downe, ſhaken together and running over Luke</hi> 8.36. what we heare then and ſee in her we muſt doe, we muſt be <hi>ready to every good worke, Tit.</hi> 3. <hi>fruitfull in every good worke, Col.</hi> 1.10. walking with <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth in all the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God without reproofe, Luke</hi> 1. and <hi>abounding alwayes in the worke of the Lord,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. what the yong man boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of vaine-gloriouſly, wee muſt ſtriue after ſincerely, <hi>all theſe haue I kept from my youth</hi> vpwardes. <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.20.</p>
            <p>For God loueth a fulneſſe of all things, an abounding in every good gift, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. a fulneſſe of knowledge, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9. a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of obedience, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.11. a fulneſſe of faith, and for that purpoſe giueth to his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6186:18"/>a fulneſſe of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Stephen full of faith, and of the holy Ghoſt, Act.</hi> 6.5. Away then with thoſe depthes of Satan, when men thinke that they may borrow a point of God, and with that yong man, <hi>Marke</hi> 10. faile in one thing or other, and with <hi>Herod, Mar.</hi> 6. keepe their minion <hi>Herodias,</hi> ſome darling ſinne or other, ſo long as they doe many good things. Let not then the vſurer flatter himſelfe with an opinion that God will be mercifull vnto him in his vſury (as <hi>Naaman</hi> prayed that God would be mercifull vnto him in the point of bowing in the idoles tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple 2. <hi>Kings.</hi> 5.) nor the adulterer in his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, nor the blaſpemer in his ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, nor the drunkard in his ſwilling, nor the ſlanderer in his evill ſpeaking, nor the louer of pleaſures in his immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and vnlawfull paſtimes, nor any man in his taking liberty to committe &amp; continue in any knowne ſinne. Our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God muſt be vniverſall, like to that which the <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6186:18"/>halfe tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> profeſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to <hi>Ioſhuah, all that thou commandeſt vs will wee doe, whitherſoever thou ſendeſt vs, will we goe, in all things as we obeyed Moſes, ſo will wee obey thee, loſ.</hi> 1.16.17. We muſt then with the Apoſtle pray that the God of peace would make vs <hi>perfect in every good worke to doe his will, Heb.</hi> 13.20.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Almeſ-deedes which ſhee did:</hi> But the holy Ghoſt here <hi>tranſit à theſi ad hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſin,</hi> paſſeth from the generall to the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, from her fulneſſe in good workes in generall, to her fulneſſe in one good worke ſpecially, and that is in almeſ-deeds. It may be ſayd, what neede this waſt of words? if ſhee were full of all good workes, then conſequently of almeſ-deedes, if ſhee abounded in every grace, then in this alſo, for <hi>Genus eſt inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabile à ſuis ſpeciebus,</hi> the generall and the ſpeciall cannot be ſeparated one from another; It is true, the one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without the other, but very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in ſcripture, where wee finde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6186:19"/>&amp; good works me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned, we ſhall ſee giving of almes attend vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as an elder daughter vpon the mother. <hi>Cornelius</hi> being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended for <hi>a devout man, &amp; one that feared God,</hi> this point is preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly added, <hi>he gaue muchalmes to the people, Act.</hi> 10.2. the Apoſtle requiring in a widow to be choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſervice of the Church, <hi>that ſhe ſhold be well reported of for good workes,</hi> preſently hitteth vpon this ſpeciall, <hi>if ſhe haue lodged ſtrangers, if ſhe haue waſhed the Saints feet, if ſhee haue relieued the afflicted,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.10. and calling vpon the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> that they ſhould <hi>not forget to doe good,</hi> in the next place he addeth <hi>and to communicate, Heb.</hi> 13.16. either joyning the ſpeciall to the generall, communicating to doing of good, or by both words ſignifying one thing, becauſe diſtributing to the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our brethren is <hi>magna pars bonorum operum,</hi> a great and principall part of good works; it is (as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> ſayd pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation was in Rhetoricke) <hi>primum, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, &amp; tertium in benefaciendo;</hi> the firſt,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6186:19"/>ſecond and third point in doing of good. Yea conſider how great a good worke almeſ doing is, ſeeing it ſhall be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned when all our other workes ſhall be omitted: <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father &amp;c. for I was hungry, and yee fedde me, I was thirſty, and ye gaue me drinke Matt.</hi> 25.34.35. <hi>tacet Deus &amp;c. God concealeth all the other good deedes of the righteous, and onely vouchſafeth to remember their almes, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealeth alſo all the evill deedes of vngodly men, and onely thinketh meete to rebuke their barrenneſſe in almes. Auguſtine</hi> in his 28. Homily. and <hi>Peter Chryſologus</hi> in his 14. Sermon, <hi>In the kingdome of heaven before all, in the aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that riſe, God mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that</hi> Abel <hi>ſuffred, that</hi> Noah <hi>preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the world, that</hi> Abraham <hi>kept the faith, that</hi> Moſes <hi>gaue the law, that</hi> Peter <hi>aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vp to the croſſe of Ieſus with his heeles vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, but only ſpeaketh of that which the pore eateth:</hi> and ſeeing our riches ſo loſt (as the world thinketh) ſhall be found, when all the treaſures that we lay vp cloſely ſhal be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6186:20"/>loſt, for as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſayth, <hi>by keeping earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things we looſe them, but by giving of them we preſerue them:</hi> and as <hi>Peter Chryſologus, whatſoever thou giueſt to the poore, thou ſhalt haue it, whatſoever thou giueſt not to the poore, another ſhall haue it.</hi> The point to be preſſed to vs hence, is as plaine as <hi>Abacuckes</hi> viſion, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.2. <hi>hee may runne that readeth</hi> and obſerveth it. It is that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Diſciple of the houſhold of faith muſt <hi>pro ſuo modulo,</hi> according to his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, abound in this grace of diſtributing, the rich muſt <hi>be rich in good workes, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17. They muſt caſt great gifts into Chriſts treaſury, the meaner ſort muſt not be wanting in their mites, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12. and every one according to his ability muſt relieue his brethren, for ſo they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion it at <hi>Antioch, Act.</hi> 11.29. yea and in caſe of neceſſity ſometimes beyond his ability, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3. But who is ſuch a ſtranger in our <hi>Iſraell,</hi> that hee knoweth not theſe things? I may ſay of this point
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6186:20"/>as <hi>Luther</hi> ſayd of that verſe of the 15. <hi>Pſ: he that hath not giuen his money vpon vſury. Iſte verſus non indiget expoſitione, ſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletione,</hi> this verſe needes no expounding but fulfilling. Inſtruction in this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe wee neede not but rather corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for our being behinde in this worke of the Lord. Amongſt vs that are called Chriſtians, there are many profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, fewe practiſers, and thoſe fewe that ſeeme ready to other good workes, are backward inough to this. I will not ſay with the Apoſtle 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>I speake it to our ſhame,</hi> that little of this fruit grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon many of thoſe trees, that ſeeme not onely to haue beene long planted, but alſo much to flouriſh in the Courts of Gods houſe, that this ſure marke of ſound religion is almoſt worne out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many, who yet <hi>primos ſe volunt eſſe in religione</hi> would be ringleaders in religion, but I will take vp thoſe words of <hi>Naaman,</hi> 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 5. <hi>God be mercifull vnto vs in this</hi> point, and double them
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6186:21"/>with him, <hi>God be mercifull vnto vs in this</hi> point, for want of ſhewing our pure and vndefiled religion before God by the workes of mercy towards our brethren, for failing in this fruit of our faith, and proofe of our being true worſhippers of God, <hi>caeteris rebus pietatem colimus,</hi> in other matters we ſhew our ſelues very godly, we can goe vp to Gods temple, ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in his houſe, make many praiers vnto him, ſhew much loue with our mouthes, but when it commeth to this hand-loue, then our hearts goe after co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31, we loue that the bread of life ſhould dwell plenteouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, but very ſparingly deale our bread to the hungry, we can continue in breaking of bread at Gods table, but care not for breaking our bread to his people, we can ſing luſtily with a good courage, but not giue cheerefully, which God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, we can perhaps faſt, and afflict our ſoules, (but that is not in much vſe with vs) but wee cannot refreſh the bowels
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6186:21"/>of Gods poore people, wee rather make them faſt, and afflict their ſoules; in a word, wee are forwarder to ſhew our religion and loue to Gods name any way then this way. The old people of the <hi>Iewes</hi> were very ſtrict in all other fruits of their religion, <hi>they ſought God dayly, and delighted to know his wayes, as a nation that did righteouſly, and forſooke not the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their God, they asked of God the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of juſtice, they tooke delight in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching to God, they faſted, they afflicted their ſoules:</hi> and thought theſe ſuch high points of piety that they quarrelled with God for not regarding of them. <hi>VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue we faſted,</hi> ſay they, <hi>and thou ſeeſt not? wherefore haue we afflicted our ſoule, and thou takeſt no knowledge?</hi> but all this religion and devotion was in vaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the workes of Charity. <hi>Is not this the faſt that I haue choſen? to looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, to vndoe the heavy burdens, and to let the oppreſſed go free, and that ye breake every yoake? Is it not to deale thy bread to the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6186:22"/>hungry, and that thou bring the poore that are caſt out to thine houſe, when thou ſeeſt the naked that thou cover him, and that thou hide not thy ſelfe from thine owne fleſh? Iſa</hi> 58.2.3.5.6.7. That of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Baſile</hi> in an Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the vnmercifull rich men of his time, is very appliable to ours; <hi>I haue knowne them that haue faſted, that haue pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that haue ſighed and groaned, and in a word haue exerciſed and practiſed all the workes of piety that would coſt them nothing, but would not bestow one halfe-penny on the poore, what profit had they of all their other vertue?</hi> It was excellently ſayd of <hi>Leo</hi> in his ſermon <hi>de apparit. the vertue of mercy is ſo great, that without it, the rest though they be preſent cannot profit: for although a man be faithfull, and chast, and ſober, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with other excellent gifts, yet if he be not mercifull, he ſhall not obtaine mercy.</hi> But on every ſide we may finde <hi>Iudaſſes</hi> that care not for the poore, nay care not ſo much as for a ſhew of caring for the poore, which was in him, <hi>this ointment
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6186:22"/>might haue beene ſold for three hundred pence, and giuen to the poore, Iohn</hi> 12.5.6. Churliſh <hi>Nabals,</hi> that being moved to a worke of mercy can roare out, <hi>ſhall I take my bread, and my water, and my fleſh that I haue killed for my ſhearers, and giue it to men whom I know not whence they bee?</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.11. Their hearts even in this reſpect are ſtony, inſenſible of others miſeries, the bowels of compaſſion are ſhut vp in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſtrately as the gates of <hi>Iericho</hi> were <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 7.1. their eyes are evill and cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to ſee another eate of their morſels, their hands are withered like the mans in the Goſpell, <hi>Luke</hi> 6. ſo that they cannot open and ſtretch them out to their poore brother. Let <hi>Lazarus</hi> lie, and cry, and dye at their gates, they will pitty him leſſe then their dogges; with <hi>Cain</hi> they will be no keepers of their brethren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. Let Gods miniſters ſerue at the Altar, and cry with the children of the Prophets <hi>mors est in olla</hi> death is in the potte, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 4.40. for their poore maintenance,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6186:23"/>they will not receiue them, nor giue them a cuppe of cold water in the name of a Prophet. <hi>The Lord hath neede of them, Matt.</hi> 21.3. is no plea with them to make them part with an Aſſe, or the foale of an Aſſe, or the hoofe of an Aſſe for Gods ſervice. Let them haue enough in ſtore for themſelues, <hi>lie vpon their beds of Ivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, stretch themſelues vpon their coaches, eate the lambes out of the flocke, and the calues out of the midst of the stall, drinke wine in boules, and annoint themſelues with chiefe oyntment, and they will not grieue for the affliction of Ioſeph, Am.</hi> 6.4.5.6. they will haue no compaſſion on the multitude that haue nothing to eate, <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.2. Lord lay not this ſin of vnmercifulneſſe to the charge of this age of ours, and ſtirre vs vp in our places, and according to our powers, to ſhew mercy here, that wee may finde it in the great day of the Lord IESVS. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6186:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
